<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC5480 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5480.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="1"?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-irtf-cfrg-spake2-03" submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title>SPAKE2, a PAKE</title>
    <author fullname="Watson Ladd" initials="W." surname="Ladd">
      <organization>UC Berkeley</organization>
      <address>
	<email>watsonbladd@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author role="editor" initials="B." surname="Kaduk" fullname="Benjamin Kaduk">
      <organization abbrev="Akamai">Akamai Technologies</organization>
      <address>
	<email>kaduk@mit.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2017"/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This Internet-Draft describes SPAKE2, a secure, efficient password
	based key exchange protocol.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes a means for two parties that share a password
	to derive a shared key. This method is compatible with any group, is
	computationally efficient, and has a strong security proof.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="definition" title="Definition of SPAKE2">
      <section title="Setup">
	<t>Let G be a group in which the Diffie-Hellman problem is hard of
	  order ph, with p a big prime and h a cofactor. We denote the
	  operations in the group additively. Let H be a hash function from
	  arbitrary strings to bit strings of a fixed length. Common choices
	  for H are SHA256 or SHA512. We assume there is a representation of
	  elements of G as byte strings: common choices would be SEC1
	  uncompressed <xref target="SEC1" /> for elliptic curve groups or big
	  endian integers of a particular length for prime field DH.</t>

	<t>|| denotes concatenation of strings. We also let len(S) denote the
	  length of a string in bytes, represented as an eight-byte little-
	  endian number.</t>

	<t>We fix two elements M and N as defined in the table in this document
	  for common groups, as well as a generator G of the group. G is
	  specified in the document defining the group, and so we do not recall
	  it here.</t>

	<t>Let A and B be two parties. We will assume that A and B are also
	  representations of the parties such as MAC addresses or other names
	  (hostnames, usernames, etc). We assume they share an integer w.
	  Typically w will be the hash of a user-supplied password, truncated
	  and taken mod p. Protocols using this protocol must define the method
	  used to compute w: it may be necessary to carry out normalization.
	  The hashing algorithm SHOULD be designed to slow down brute force
	  attackers.</t>

	<t>We present two protocols below. Note that it is insecure to use the
	  same password with both protocols, this MUST NOT be done.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="SPAKE2">
	<t>A picks x randomly and uniformly from the integers in [0,ph)
	  divisible by h, and calculates X=xG and T=wM+X, then transmits T to
	  B.</t>

	<t>B selects y randomly and uniformly from the integers in [0,ph),
	  divisible by h and calculates Y=yG, S=wN+Y, then transmits S to A.</t>

	<t>Both A and B calculate a group element K. A calculates it as
	  x(S-wN), while B calculates it as y(T-wM). A knows S because it has
	  received it, and likewise B knows T.</t>

	<t>This K is a shared secret, but the scheme as described is not secure.
	  K  MUST be combined with the values transmitted and received via a
	  hash function to have a secure protocol. If higher-level protocols
	  prescribe a method for doing so, that SHOULD be used. Otherwise we
	  can compute K' as H(len(A)||A||len(B)||B||len(S)||S||
	  len(T)||T||len(K)||K || len(w) || w) and use K' as the key.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="SPAKE2+">
	<t>This protocol and security proof appear in <xref target="TDH" />. We
	  use the same setup as for SPAKE2, except that we have two secrets, w0
	  and w1. The server, here Bob, stores L=w1*g and w0.</t>

	<t>When executing SPAKE2+, A selects x uniformly at random from the
	  numbers in the range [0, ph) divisible by h, and lets X=xG+w0*M, then
	  transmits X to B. B selects y uniformly at random from the numbers in
	  [0, ph) divisible by h, then computes Y=yG+w0*N, and transmits it to
	  Alice.</t>

	<t>A computes Z as x(Y-w0*N), and V as w1(Y-w0*N). B computes Z as y(X-
	  w0*M) and V as yL. Both share Z and V as common keys. It is essential
	  that both Z and V be used in combination with the transcript to
	  derive the keying material. For higher-level protocols without
	  sufficient transcript hashing, let K' be
	  H(len(A)||A||len(B)||B||len(X)||X||len(Y)||Y||len(Z)||Z||len(V)||V)
	  and use K' as the established key.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Table of points for common groups">
      <t>Every curve presented in the table below has an OID from <xref
	target="RFC5480" />. We construct a string using the OID and the needed
	constant, for instance "1.3.132.0.35 point generation seed (M)" for
	P-512.  This string is turned into an infinite sequence of bytes by
	hashing with SHA256, and hashing that output again to generate the next
	32 bytes, and so on. This pattern is repeated for each group and value,
	with the string modified appropriately.</t>

      <t>The initial segment of bytes of length equal to that of an encoded
	group element is taken, and is then formatted as required for the
	group.  In the case of Weierstrass points, this means setting the first
	byte to 0x02 or 0x03 depending on the low-order bit. For Ed25519 style
	formats this means taking all the bytes as the representation of the
	group element.  This string of bytes is then interpreted as a point in
	the group. If this is impossible, then the next non-overlapping segment
	of sufficient length is taken. We multiply that point by the cofactor
	h, and if that is not the identity, output it.</t>

      <t>These bytestrings are compressed points as in <xref target="SEC1" />
	for curves from <xref target="SEC1" />.</t>

      <t>For P256:</t>

      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
M =
02886e2f97ace46e55ba9dd7242579f2993b64e16ef3dcab95afd497333d8fa12f

N =
03d8bbd6c639c62937b04d997f38c3770719c629d7014d49a24b4f98baa1292b49
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>For P384:</t>

      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
M =
030ff0895ae5ebf6187080a82d82b42e2765e3b2f8749c7e05eba366434b363d3dc
36f15314739074d2eb8613fceec2853

N =
02c72cf2e390853a1c1c4ad816a62fd15824f56078918f43f922ca21518f9c543bb
252c5490214cf9aa3f0baab4b665c10
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>For P521:</t>

      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
M =
02003f06f38131b2ba2600791e82488e8d20ab889af753a41806c5db18d37d85608
cfae06b82e4a72cd744c719193562a653ea1f119eef9356907edc9b56979962d7aa

N =
0200c7924b9ec017f3094562894336a53c50167ba8c5963876880542bc669e494b25
32d76c5b53dfb349fdf69154b9e0048c58a42e8ed04cef052a3bc349d95575cd25
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>The following python snippet generates the above points:</t>

      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
def canon_pointstr(self, s):
    return chr(ord(s[0]) & 1 | 2) + s[1:]

def iterated_hash(seed, n):
    h = seed
    for i in xrange(n):
	h = SHA256.new(h).digest()
    return h

def bighash(seed, start, sz):
    n = -(-sz // 32)
    hashes = [iterated_hash(seed, i) for i in xrange(start, start + n)]
    return ''.join(hashes)[:sz]

def gen_point(seed, ec, order):
    for i in xrange(1, 1000):
	pointstr = ec.canon_pointstr(bighash(seed, i, ec.nbytes_point()))
	try:
	    p = ec.decode_point(pointstr)
	    if ec.mul(p, order) == ec.identity():
		return pointstr, i
	except Exception:
	    pass
]]></artwork></figure>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>A security proof of SPAKE2 for prime order groups is found in <xref
	  target="REF" />.  Note that the choice of M and N is critical for the
	security proof.  The generation method specified in this document is
	designed to eliminate concerns related to knowing discrete logs of M
	and N.</t>

      <t>SPAKE2+ appears in <xref target="TDH" />, along with proof.</t>

      <t>There is no key-confirmation as this is a one round protocol. It is
	expected that a protocol using this key exchange mechanism provides key
	confirmation separately if desired.</t>

      <t>Elements should be checked for group membership: failure to properly
	validate group elements can lead to attacks. In particular it is
	essential to verify that received points are valid compressions of
	points on an elliptic curve when using elliptic curves. It is not
	necessary to validate membership in the prime order subgroup: the
	multiplication by cofactors eliminates this issue.</t>

      <t>The choices of random numbers MUST BE uniform. Note that to pick a
	random multiple of h in [0, ph) one can pick a random integer in [0,p)
	and multiply by h. Reuse of ephemerals results in dictionary attacks
	and MUST NOT be done.</t>

      <t>SPAKE2 does not support augmentation. As a result, the server has to
	store a password equivalent. This is considered a significant drawback,
	and so SPAKE2+ also appears in this document.</t>

      <t>As specified the shared secret K is not suitable for use as a shared
	key.  It MUST be passed to a hash function along with the public values
	used to derive it and the party identities to avoid attacks.  In
	protocols which do not perform this separately, the value denoted K'
	MUST be used instead.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>No IANA action is required.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Special thanks to Nathaniel McCallum for generation of test vectors.
	Thanks to Mike Hamburg for advice on how to deal with cofactors. Greg
	Hudson suggested addition of warnings on the reuse of x and y. Thanks
	to Fedor Brunner, Adam Langley, and the members of the CFRG for
	comments and advice. Trevor Perrin informed me of SPAKE2+.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="References">
      <reference anchor="REF">
	<front>
	  <title>Simple Password-Based Encrypted Key Exchange Protocols.</title>
	  <author initials="M." surname="Abdalla" />
	  <author initials="D." surname="Pointcheval" />
	  <date month="Feb" year="2005" />
	</front>
	<annotation>Appears in A. Menezes, editor. Topics in
	  Cryptography-CT-RSA 2005, Volume 3376 of Lecture Notes in Computer
	  Science, pages 191-208, San Francisco, CA, US.  Springer-Verlag,
	  Berlin, Germany.
	</annotation>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="SEC1">
	<front>
	  <title>STANDARDS FOR EFFICIENT CRYPTOGRAPHY, "SEC 1: Elliptic Curve
	    Cryptography", version 2.0</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>SEC</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date month="May" year="2009" />
	</front>
	<format type="PDF" target="http://www.sec.org/sec1-v2.pdf" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="TDH">
	<front>
	  <title>The Twin-Diffie Hellman Problem and Applications</title>
	  <author initials="D." surname="Cash" />
	  <author initials="E." surname="Kiltz" />
	  <author initials="V." surname="Shoup" />
	  <date year="2008" />
	</front>
	<annotation>EUROCRYPT 2008.  Volume 4965 of Lecture notes in Computer
	  Science, pages 127-145.  Springer-Verlag, Berlin, Germany.
	</annotation>
      </reference>
      &RFC5480;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
